my name's garland nixon and i'm john
kiriakou
and the united states has finally left
afghanistan after a 20-year invasion and
subsequent occupation plenty for john
and i to talk about and we want your
feedback let's talk
[Music]
so my name is garland nixon and i'm here
with my good friend john kiriakou john
and i are going to start doing a lot of
stuff online together um and i'm looking
forward to it make sure you follow me at
garland nixon on twitter of course at
john
and keep an eye on us we're going to be
doing a lot also make sure everything
that we do you share it on all your
social media platforms good evening john
this is i think we're going to have a
lot of fun i'm looking forward to doing
a lot of good shows together i've i have
to agree garland i've been looking
forward to this for a long time and uh
boy there's a lot to talk about there
really is i mean 20 years and
here's what i'd like to like let's just
dive right into it because i want to ask
you something about you know a lot about
the area you know you worked in pakistan
you worked in the area and the first
thing i thought about was
the
how fast
um
afghan i don't even know to call them
that but the afghan military such as it
was melted away
fell away and i just thought that you
know it seemed to me that
a soldier that doesn't feel like they
have a legitimate government to fight
for that doesn't have anything to fight
for just either negotiates or walks away
what are your thoughts about why the
afghan military just disappeared melted
away almost
let's be realistic it was overnight they
didn't fight
it was uh in fact president biden said
uh in public that he believed the
central government could hold on for six
more months in fact it held on for six
days a huge huge difference and the
problems in the military garland were
several fold first of all
most of the the afghans who were
recruited into the afghan
military and the afghan national police
didn't really want to be there it was a
job they knew that the americans paid
their bills
so you know it was it was something they
could do to make a couple of dollars
there was no real commitment to a
central government there was no
commitment to protecting the country um
secondly
a lot of those guys
were at least ideologically
taliban or taliban sympathizers
and third
the the military controlled really very
little of afghanistan we used to joke
even 10 years ago
when i was on the senate foreign
relations committee staff that
that hamid karzai was really no more
than the mayor of kabul you know there
was this this false belief
that the the central government of
afghanistan controlled the countryside
or controlled much of the country that's
just simply not true they controlled
really very little and and fourth there
were serious tribal issues you know
there were pashtuns who wouldn't work
with hazaras and tajiks who wouldn't
work with pashtuns and uzbeks who didn't
want to work with anybody and
people just hated each other there was
one terrible incident in 2012
where um dyncorp was was uh
training people for both the military
and the police uh one of the recruits
was a taliban sympathizer and he put
poison he put arsenic into a pot of stew
and poisoned um
many of his of his compatriots he killed
about a dozen of them wow and then that
night he
opened the door and let other members of
the taliban into the dormitory and they
they stabbed most of the other recruits
to death wow so that's what we were up
against you know from the very beginning
this was this was really a western a
western style military that we were
trying to impose on this country that
has never had a western-style military
yeah it seems to me that that's i i
can't remember where i read this but
years ago i read someone wrote an
article about um the us and the middle
east and they said the problem is we
look at the middle east and we see
america and we try to rebuild america
and we try to build the type of
bureaucracy that we have here we try to
build a military with a type of
bureaucracy that our military works
which i might add may be one of the
reasons that it's ineffective in that
region you know because it's a our
military is built to fight
you know it's all you know what it
reminds me of it reminds me of the
revolutionary war where the
uh the british soldiers were
you know taught to fight by the
queensberry rules you know suicide
pretty much you know when you stand in a
line and you shoot and they shoot back
and you all die you know it's pretty
stupid but that's what they were trained
and the um
you know the americans kind of did what
they had to do they fought from trees
and roadsides and they took advantage of
that and it seems to me that it's the
same type of empire fighting a ragtag
group of people who live in the
countryside and that's what we do in
um
in the middle east particularly in
afghanistan and as they the the the the
a lot of the shiites say in in the
middle east you got the watches we got
the time
you know i was in afghanistan in 2007 as
a private citizen i went on behalf of
paramount studios which is a whole
different story but uh one of my
meetings was with the leader of the
hazaras in
uh in kabul and the hazaras of course
are an ethnic minority they have more in
common with the iranians than they have
with the costumes that run afghanistan
and they're shia muslims right well in
this guy's living room he had a large
shadow box mounted on the wall and it
had every one of his judo belts from
from white to you know fifth level black
and i congratulated him on it and he
said do you know why i'm a black belt in
judo do you know why every hazara
studies judo
and i said no
and he said because we are forbidden by
law
from carrying a weapon
it's the only way that we can protect
ourselves now this was after
six years of u.s occupation wow this is
after the us imposed a democratic
government and there was still still
such strife
such intercommunal strife between sunnis
and shias that shias weren't even
allowed to defend themselves
well so the reality is while the u.s
claimed that we were we claimed to we're
going to basically impose a
western-style government on there a
liberal democracy etc
we s
and and and i got to add this
let me let me throw this at you and tell
me if you've heard about it and what you
know about this because i've only heard
rumors
and i've seen articles but i never
looked in depth that literally there
were
afghan soldiers afghan politicians who
had child sex slaves
and that our government instructed our
diplomatic personnel and our military
personnel to ignore it have you heard
the are you familiar with those stories
yeah those stories are true um it's
something that i try to address uh at
the senate foreign relations committee
uh it's a it's a
it's a cultural thing
where um pashtun men
have sex with
uh with boys young boys uh provided that
they're unable to grow a beard because
it's not considered to be homosexual if
they're children as crazy as that sounds
and so what they'll do this was actually
in the book the kite runner and the
movie the kite runner
what they'll do is they'll they'll
purchase these boys from poor families
and have them work as t-boys as valets
um
they'll make them do
homoerotic dances for for entertainment
and they'll have sex with them and this
is seen as something that's that's quite
acceptable because it has you know a
millennia-long uh uh history
and so when we went there and were
justifiably appalled at the way children
were being treated our soldiers were
told and and more than just our soldiers
everybody who was in afghanistan was
told this is cultural it's not for us to
judge and we just let it go
you know it's kind of like the heroin
trade
garland we could do an entire show just
on heroin poppy but i went to
afghanistan in
2009 to do a study on poppy cultivation
and the military was not happy about
this at all because they had to fly me
all around the country i wanted to meet
with poppy farmers and distributors and
you know drug lords and
people spoke freely about it but i i
went to the village of lush garga which
is the capital of hellmann province and
almost all of the country's heroin came
from helmand and from kandahar right
right so i went out into the fields and
i
i met up with a poppy farmer and i very
naively asked him
why instead of poppy he didn't grow
something with two growing seasons like
onions or pomegranates or tomatoes
and he was just exasperated and he said
oh
he said you know
the americans told me in 2001 that if i
told them where the arabs were that i
could grow all the poppy i wanted and
now you come here and you tell me i
can't grow poppy
and i said i said what american told you
you could grow poppy
and as soon as the words came out of my
mouth my military handler said meeting
over we have to go and the guy literally
pulled me back onto the helicopter
and and we we left i i wrote it up as
best i could but the message was clear
you know i i was told later by a dea
officer
that
afghanistan produces 93 of the world's
heroin
and almost all of it goes to iran and
russia right you don't care if iranians
and russians are addicted to heroin
you one might
knowing the history of our intelligence
agency one might make the argument that
they would encourage uh you know if you
look at the history you'll look back at
the british empire and the opium wars
etc sometimes it could be it is
encouraged as a method of uh another
underhanded kind of warfare i would
agree i would agree
so you know it i tell you the other part
of it too is this
and that is what you're talking about it
to me is one of the reasons that the us
or any empire should not be going around
the world trying to
rebuild the world in its own image you
know i know i you know i've traveled in
south america and i've gone you know
i've been fortunate enough to go to some
small villages and talk to people in
south america venezuela different places
and as an example coca
what you find is that there are
areas in the
you know in these different places but
there are areas where that's the only
way these people can make a living that
if you were to say you can't grow your
coca leaves anymore which is processed
and turned into cocaine if you can't do
that everybody in the area would
basically starve and you'd have a civil
war the government would be overthrown i
mean it was just it would completely
destabilize everything so while it's may
seem like a bad thing in the
um in the grand scheme of things
from the perspective of the people who
are living in those areas that's their
only option
i i think you're exactly right that is
their only option and you know
we we bring this very american mindset
to the problem too uh when i was in
afghanistan uh there was a lieutenant
colonel there who asked
very pointedly why don't we just spray
roundup on everything we'll just fly
over these fields and just
you know like with one of these crop
dusters just spray everything with
roundup
and the us ambassador said
oh that would be just great and then as
soon as
we see the first birth defect
in a villager or the first evidence of
down syndrome
they're gonna blame the roundup and
they're going to blame the americans and
then we have a whole different fight on
our hands
yeah and and so again what we're talking
about are things that
to me this is all the reason that you
you you you shouldn't be there because
in reality
you cannot change a society if you have
a society that's been doing things a
particular way for ten thousand years
five thousand let's just say hundreds or
thousands of years in many cases we go
there and i tend to believe one of two
things that or maybe they're not
mutually exclusive
the people who run our foreign policy
are such
ideologues
to a point that it makes them fools you
know they that it's not that they don't
believe it's that they do group think
and they believe things that are not in
keeping with the reality and they
continue to try to push their beliefs
onto the world number one but number two
that
after this process gets going they they
say we're gonna go in afghanistan we're
gonna do whatever oh we're gonna make it
a wonderful place it'll be a you know a
regular new york city yeah right but at
any rate good luck with that but
once that process gets starts get gets
going
the money starts flowing
in the good times and everybody there is
getting paid and they're handing money
out i heard a guy to say to me that he
was in the military and he was there and
he would be given hundreds of thousands
of dollars in cash every month to hand
out to the villagers
and that
he basically what he said was you know
when i was there i didn't take any of
that money and i pocketed it he said but
other people did and he says and in
hindsight i probably should have
he said because i could have thrown it
in my duffel bag we just got on our
planes and came home and he says in
hindsight i could have did it and he
says other people did it but that's the
other part of it that you're there in an
area where there's corruption and then
you're just shoveling money you're
recreating the corruption and then our
people go there and now they're getting
a piece of the corruption and now you
get a society you get an you get a
dynamic where there's a country that
nobody wants to leave because they're
getting paid man they are getting paid
well and there's just cash flowing
everywhere that's not being accounted
for
i can't tell you how many times
over the years that i was with the cia
that i took delivery of millions of
dollars in cash
in duffel bags i'm proud to say that we
accounted for literally every last
dollar
i i spent probably 10 million in
cash maybe more than 10 million it was
probably around 10 million in cash when
i was the head of counter-terrorism
operations in pakistan but we accounted
for every single dollar
i'm not at all surprised that other
elements of the us government couldn't
account for their money um and it's
because intelligence and warfighting
garland is a cash business
and
you know i i was driving
i was driving one day from islamabad to
uh to lahore with a colleague and we had
two million dollars in two duffel bags
and i said to him you know i always used
to joke whenever we would hear that
somebody at the agency had been fired or
was being prosecuted for stealing you
know six hundred dollars or a thousand
dollars i always used to think man if
you're going to steal something steal
millions you're right still still enough
to retire on exactly from here we were
driving just the two of us with two
million dollars in cash and we looked at
each other and just started laughing
because even with the millions you got a
job to do and your country trusts you
and the american people trust you and so
you have to do the right thing well and
let me ask you this
we're going to get out of here we're
only going to do about 20 minutes what
are your thoughts i tell you um there
was
as we left there was the attack on the
airport yes and the u.s then said oh
well you know biden said oh we're going
to strike back of course a drone strike
and i've done a lot of research it
certainly appears that there was a
family of nine that was killed yes um
and to me that's kind of emblematic of
the whole
isn't it those two things
we we're there to quote fight terrorism
as we leave a car bomb goes off kills a
bunch of people including in in
including 13 soldiers and then we go to
strike back as it were and kill a family
if not a killer family if not that's all
of afghanistan to me those two things
are all of our policies in the middle
east all summed up in one and that's why
it's counterproductive to what we claim
we're trying to
do what are your thoughts on that i
agree and you know seven of those nine
were children and five of them were
under the age of five wow the drone
program is a is is an act of terrorism
as far as i'm concerned we can certainly
talk about that at length at some point
but you're right i i'll say too that
that had the suicide bomber not killed
um
uh what was it 12 marines and a sailor
yeah um i think that that this
evacuation would have gone down as as a
major success at the end of the day
because we've gotten out tens of
thousands of people americans
allies
afghans who had worked for the u.s
government or for the u.s military
without those 13 deaths we wouldn't have
had this last drone strike and we would
have been able to get out with no loss
of life um it got ugly at the end and
another thing that bothers me is
the government wants us to believe that
this don't drone strike killed two isis
k leaders uh they've not identified who
those leaders are which leads me to
think that no isis k leaders were killed
this was just an innocent family that
was killed and we're trying to put the
best face on it
yeah and you know it's kind of like um
syria and iraq for many years every
other week you ever noticed we always
killed the second in command of al-qaeda
or isis it was always every couple weeks
guess who we killed outback daddy we
killed him about a dozen and a half
times that guy had more lives than a cat
so it gets to a point where you realize
that
um there's a certain level of propaganda
and the gov our government won't and
can't simply say oh oops darn we
accidentally killed a family oops sorry
about that they can't ever do that and
so what we end up creating is a bunch of
people that hate us and and you know
you know you've got kids i've got got a
daughter if that happened to my child
i'd be i'd want some you know i'd i'd be
angry i'd want revenge i might be a
terrorist if that happened most people
would
and so we're creating terrorism by doing
that by not using diplomacy in the
middle east and really to be quite
honest not allowing the governments that
have
strategic interests in the area you know
what i mean i mean regardless of how the
us gets along with iran iran has
strategic interest in um keeping
terrorism from incubating in iran and
iran you know what i mean the countries
on the border china russia has uh was it
uzbekistan or tajikistan that's right on
the border both right so they have all
of these countries have a strategic
interest in maintaining some level of um
stability there and the us won't just
simply say hey we'll work with you to
have a stable area it's almost like uh
you know we'd rather have an unstable
area than have our
i'll put it like this an unstable
area that makes life harder for iran and
russia and china etc um even if it
causes us problems
i think that's exactly right and and we
have to recognize too that we can't be
everywhere in the world i have to hand
it to the chinese i think the chinese
have really played this right they
maintained good relations with the
afghan government and at the same time
they may in good relations with the
taliban
uh several years ago six years ago they
signed an exclusive agreement with the
afghan government to mine rare earth
metals it's worth a trillion dollars and
that deal is being respected by the
taliban so uh you know the chinese
didn't lose anybody the chinese didn't
drone anybody and the chinese the ones
who are going to end up making money out
of this whole deal and and your last
thing we'll touch base on i think i look
at a country like china some of the
countries china and russia particularly
and
one of the things that they do that i
think we'd be far better off and that is
they'll do business with you they won't
they can say we don't like your style of
government we think you're doing
terrible things blah blah blah but
we're not going to interfere in your
internal affairs if we can make money
you want to buy our oil you want to buy
our gas or we need your oil or your gas
will buy it what you do there is your
business to me when i look at what's
happening with china's economy
as fast as it's growing and ours is
is is you know
struggling in our people are getting
angry there's more division etc and i
think you know we'd be far better off if
we'd actually take our noses out of
other people's businesses look here and
try to adjust the problems we have with
the pandemic and the evictions and all
that stuff but we're so it's like our
government doesn't give a crap about the
people we got to go around the
world and stick our nose in everybody
else's business and try to fix them when
we're broke yes
it's it's sad but true and it's a lesson
that we just don't seem to learn look at
all the different places that we've been
bogged down in just in the last 20 years
since september 11th
you know we can talk about
afghanistan and iraq and syria and yemen
and somalia and libya and uh you know
there's an argument even to be made for
venezuela
when do we learn yeah i do want to talk
to you i want to get back on soon and i
want to talk about pakistan and how they
fit into this because the fact of the
matter is the pakistan um intelligence
agency i mean you can argue the u.s kind
of built the
um you know founded the militant
islamist movement in the late
70s you know and throughout the 80s to
push back against the soviet union
something again that i disagree with
because it was at least stable under the
former what was that
the people something party of
afghanistan right but whatever it was
but it was stable at any rate but i know
pakistan had a lot to do with building
the taliban creating the taliban funding
the taliban and i think there's a lot
more that they're going to be a big
player going forward in dealing with
taliban 2.0 and you spent a lot of time
in in pakistan so we'll get together
soon and uh within the next day or so
we'll talk about that also i want
everybody to know john and i are with
thursdays may be the day but we're going
to pick a day one day of the week and
we're going to talk about um
whistleblowers we're going to talk about
john we're going to talk about julian
assange we're going to talk about um
daniel hale
um
and we're we're gonna have a great time
so thanks a lot john
thank you darling look forward to
talking to you soon everyone share this
on all of your social media platforms
follow at garland knicks and follow at
john kiriakou let people know john and i
are going to be doing a lot of shows and
a lot of stuff together we're looking
forward to it thanks we are out